In the last video, you and I looked at this demo here
在上集视频中  我们观看了这个演示
where we shine linearly polarized light through a tube full of sugar water
我们用线偏振光照射装满糖水的圆筒
and we saw how it rather mysteriously results in these coloured diagonal stripes.
并看见它会产生这些神秘的彩色斜条纹
There I walked through the general outline for an explanation
我当时描述了解释这一现象的大致框架
keeping track of what questions still need to be answered,
并记录了有哪些问题仍然需要解答
namely: why does sugar water twist the polarization direction of light?
即：为什么糖水会扭曲光的偏振方向？
Why does that twisting rate depend on the colour of the light
为什么扭曲率取决于光的颜色？
and why even if you understand that this twist is happening,
还有  即使你知道这种扭曲会发生
would you see any evidence of it
但为什么从侧面观察糖水管时
when viewing the tube from the side with no additional polarizing filters?
在没有额外偏振片的情况下  你仍能看到任何扭曲的迹象呢？
Here I'd like to begin with the very fundamental idea of what light is
在这里  我想先从“光是什么”这个最基本的概念入手
and show how the answers to these questions
给观众展示  这些问题的答案是如何
can emerge from an extremely minimal set of assumptions.
从一组极其简单的假设中产生的
In some sense, the fundamental question of electricity and magnetism
从某种意义上  电学和磁学的基本问题
is how the position and motion of one charged particle
是一个带电粒子的位置和运动  如何影响另一个带电粒子
influences that of another.
For example, one of the first things you learn, say in a high school physics class
例如  你在高中物理课上学到的第一项知识
is that charges with the same sign tend to repel each other.
或许就是电荷同性相斥
And the strength of this force depends a lot on the distance between them.
而这种力的强度  很大程度上取决于两者的间距
If your charges are close,
如果电荷很近
that repulsive force is very strong,
相互的排斥力会很强
but it decays very rapidly as these particles go away from each other.
但是随着这些粒子相互远离  这种排斥力会迅速减弱
Specificaly, here's how you might see this written down as an equation
具体来说  你可以将这个问题写成公式
known as Coulomb's law.
它就是库仑定律
The force is proportional to the charge of both of the particles
力与两个粒子的电荷（一般用q表示）分别成正比
where it's common to use the letter Q.
There are some constants in there
那里有一些常数
which for our purposes we can just think of as one big proportionality constant
我们可以把它们看作一个大的比例常数
and the important fact is that
重要的是
you've got this 1 divided by r² term where r is the distance between them.
这里还有一个 1/r² 的项   其中 r 是两个粒子之间的距离
So, for example, if the distance between them increases by a factor of three,
因此举例来说  如果粒子之间的距离增加了 3 倍
the force that they're applying to each other goes down by a factor of nine.
那它们对彼此施加的力  就会减少到原来的1/9
Another way you might see a law like this written down
另一种对这公式的理解方式
is to focus on just one charged particle
是只去关注一个带电粒子
and then say for every point in space, if there was a second charge there,
然后问：对于空间中的每一点  如果那里有第二个电荷
what force would this first charge be applying to that second one?
那么第一个电荷会对第二个电荷施加什么力呢？
And instead of describing a force per se,
与其描述这个力本身
you might see this written describing what's known as the "Electric Field",
你可能会看到这样的写法  描述所谓的“电场”
which is just a way of saying what force would be applied to a unit charge
这只是一种表达单位电荷受力情况的方式
and in this context the word "Field"
“场”在这种语境下
means there is a value associated with every single point in space.
意味着空间中的每一个点都有一个对应的值
So, the way I have it written here,
因此  按照我这里的写法
it depends on a little vector R
它取决于一个小向量 r
which would be the vector from our charge to a given point in space
也就是从我们的电荷到空间给定点的向量
and the direction of this field at all points is in the same direction as R.
而这个场在所有点的方向都与 r 的方向一致
I bring up Coulomb’s law to emphasize that it's not the full story.
我提起库仑定律  是为了强调这并不是全部
There are other ways that charges influence each other.
电荷之间还有其他相互影响的方式
For example, here's a phenomenon that this law alone could not explain.
例如  库仑定律本身无法解释这样一种现象
If you wiggle one charge up and down,
如果你上下摆动一个电荷
then after a little bit of a delay,
在稍微延迟后
a second charge some distance to its right
在其右侧一定距离处的第二个电荷
will be induced to wiggle up and down as well.
也会受到感应而上下摆动
We can write down a second law,
我们可以写下第二条定律
which you might think of as a correction term to be added to Coulomb's law
你可以把它看作是库仑定律的一个修正项
that describes what's going on here.
用来描述这里发生的事情
Suppose at some point in time, T 0, that first charge is accelerating.
假设在某个时间点 t₀  第一个电荷正在加速
Then I'll let time play forward
然后我会让时间开始流动
but leave on the screen a kind of ghost of that particle
但在屏幕上留下该粒子的重影
indicating where it was and how it was accelerating at this time T 0.
去显示它在 t₀ 时的位置和加速情况
After a certain delay,
经过一定的延迟后
this causes a force on the second charge
这将对第二个电荷产生一个力
and the equation describing force looks something like this...
并且描述力的方程是这样的...
So again, it's proportional to the charge of both of the particles.
所以同样  它与两个粒子的电荷量成正比
And once more, a common way to write it involves this pile of constants
并且通常的写法还是会涉及到一堆常量
that you don't really need to worry about.
你并不需要特别担心
The important factor I want you to notice
需要注意的最重要的一点是
is how the force also depends on the distance between the particles.
力如何依然取决于粒子之间的距离
But instead of decaying in proportion to R squared,
但是  它不是按照 r² 的反比例衰减
it only decays in proportion to R.
而是只按照 r 的反比例衰减
So, over long distances,
因此  在长距离上
this is the force that dominates and Coulomb's law is negligible.
这种力占主导地位  而库仑定律可以忽略不计
And then finally, it depends on the acceleration of that first particle
最后  它取决于第一个粒子的加速度
but it's not the acceleration of that particle at the current time,
但不是看该粒子在当前时间的加速度
it's whatever that acceleration was at some time in the past.
而是看过去某个时间的加速度
How far in the past depends on
多久前的过去  取决于粒子之间的距离  除以光速 c
he distance between the particles and the speed of light denoted with C.
The way to think about it is that
可以这么理解
any form of influence can't propagate any faster than this speed C.
任何形式的影响  传播速度都不可能超过光速 c
In fact, a more accurate description of Coulomb’s law
事实上  库仑定律更准确的描述
would also involve a delay term like this...
也会包括这样一个延迟项
Again, the intuitive way to read this equation is that
同样  这个方程的直观读法是
wiggling a charge in one location
在一个位置摆动一个电荷
after some delay causes a wiggle to a second charge in another location.
经过一定的延迟后  会引起另一个位置的第二个电荷的摆动
And actually the way I have it written right now is a little bit wrong -
实际上  我现在的写法有点不对
instead of the acceleration vector here, I should really be writing something like a perp
这里的加速度向量  其实应该加上垂直符号
indicating the component of that acceleration vector
表示加速度向量  与两个电荷连线所垂直的分量
which is perpendicular to the line drawn between the two charges.
In other words, when you wiggle that first charge,
换句话说  当你摆动第一个电荷时
the direction that the second charge wiggles is always perpendicular to line between them
第二个电荷摆动的方向  总是垂直于两者连线
and the amount that it wiggles gets weaker and weaker
当两电荷间的连线  与电荷一的加速度更加一致时 电荷二的晃动幅度会越来越小
when that line between them is more lined up with the initial acceleration.
As before, this is something you might see written down in a way
和之前一样  你可能会看到这样的写法
that describes a component of the electric field caused by just one charge.
它描述的是由一个电荷引起的电场分量
Again, that means what force would be applied
同样  这意味着  在空间所有可能的不同点上
to a second charge at all possible different points in space.
第二个电荷会受到什么力的作用
This component of the field is only ever non zero
只有当第一个电荷以某种方式运动时（有加速度向量时）
when our first charge is moving somehow -
when it has an acceleration vector on it.
电场的这个分量才不会为零
And because of this delay term,
并且由于这个延迟项
the effects on this field tend to radiate away from the charge.
这个场的效果像是从电荷处辐射开来
This is why I'm writing it down with the subscript "rad".
这就是为什么我用下标“rad”(辐射)来写它
This is the component of the electric field that will radiate away from a given charge.
这就是从给定电荷辐射出去的电场分量
For instance, when the charge is oscillating up and down,
例如  当电荷上下摆动时  就会产生这些传播波
you get these propagating waves
and for many of the vector fields, I'll be showing the intensity of the field
后面当我画出各种向量场时  我会把这些场的强度
as illustrated with the opacity of each little vector.
用每个小向量的透明度来表示
This radiating influence is light.
这种辐射性的影响  就是光
Or more generally, electromagnetic radiation,
或者更广义地说  电磁辐射
including things like radio waves and X-rays and all that good stuff.
包括无线电波  X 射线等
As a side note,
顺便提一句
you sometimes see this propagation described a very different way
有时你会看到这种传播的另一种非常不同的描述方式
that puts the fields front and center using what are known as "Maxwell's Equations".
把场作为主角和中心  那就是所谓的“麦克斯韦方程”
For our purposes,
就我们的目的而言
I want to focus just on this one law
我只想集中讨论前面的这一个定律
and show just how far it can take us when it comes to intuitions for light.
并说明它对理解光的直觉  已经非常有用了
For the animations I'm about to show,
我即将展示的动画
all I've really done is encoded in this one law which tells us
就是根据屏幕右上角的这个公式
what should this component of the electric fields be at every point in space
绘出空间中任意点处的这种辐射电场分量
as determined by the history of accelerations of a particular charge.
这是由电荷加速度的历史所决定的
For example, if I set that charge oscillating up and down in the Z direction
比方说  让电荷在 Z 方向上下振荡
and illustrate this component of the electric field everywhere on the XY plane,
在 XY 平面上绘出这一电场分量的强度
you see these circular propagations of equal strength in all directions.
就像这样环状向外扩散  各个方向强度相等
It's a little easier to think about if we focus on just one axis like the X axis.
盯着一条坐标轴大概会更加清楚  比如 X 轴
And at first when I made this animation,
一开始我做出这个动画的时候
I assumed that there was some kind of bug
我觉得是不是代码出错了
because near the charge it just looks crooked and wrong.
因为电荷附近看起来有些畸形
But when you think about it,
但是仔细想想
this is actually what you should expect.
这才是它应该有的样子
Because, remember,
因为  要记住
each one of these vectors is supposed to be perpendicular to
每个场强向量都应当垂直于
the line drawn between that point
它的起点和电荷曾经所在的位置的连线
and where the charge WAS at some point in the past.
At points that are far enough away from the charge,
在距离电荷充分远的地方
which is where this component of the field is what dominates anyway,
辐射电场也远大于静电场
the wiggling in the field is essentially parallel to the wiggling in the charge.
这时电场变化的方向  基本平行于点电荷的摇摆
Which is why when we think about light waves,
这就是为什么当我们考虑光波时
we are safe to think about the wiggling direction
完全可以直接认为摆动方向和传播方向垂直
as being perpendicular to the propagation direction.
Like I said, this propagation for just one charge
我已经提过  单个电荷所产生的这种传播
is equally strong in all of the directions perpendicular to its wiggling
在所有与摆动相垂直的方向上都是等大的
and really I should emphasize
需要强调的是
that the propagation does happen in all directions of three dimensional space.
传播事实上发生在三维空间的所有方向上
It's maybe a little busy to try to illustrate
在屏幕上展现整个三维空间的向量场非常混乱  就像这样
the full three dimensional vector field on screen like this.
So, it's clarifying if we just focus on say the XZ plane.
所以  为简明起见我们关注 XZ 平面
Notice how the waves here are strongest in the X direction.
注意到这里的波在 X 方向上是最强的
But it still does propagate in all other directions.
但是它在所有其他方向上也有传播
It's just that that propagation gets weaker
只是在那些更接近原来的摆动方向的方向上  传播不那么明显
in directions that are more aligned with the original wiggling.
At the extreme, the only place where there's no propagation is in the Z axis.
最极端的情况是在 Z 轴  那是唯一没有波传播的地方
Because our law has this 1 divided by R in it,
因为我们的公式分母里有个 1 / r
the strength of the wave caused by just one particle
单一电荷产生的波强度  随距离反比下降
does decay as you go further away in proportion to 1 over R.
But notice what happens if I take a whole row of charges,
但是注意  如果我取的是一整列电荷
say oriented along the Y axis
比方说沿 Y 轴分布  在 Z 方向上振荡
and I have them all start wiggling up and down in the Z direction
and I illustrate the combined effects that all of them have
我画出它们对辐射电场分量的影响之和
on this component of the electric field.
The effects of all these charges interfere deconstructively along the Y direction
它们在 Y 方向上发生相消干涉
but they interfere constructively along the X direction.
而在 X 方向上发生相长干涉
This is what it looks like
这就是一束光集中在一个方向上时的情形
for a beam of light to be concentrated along just one dimension.
So, if you were to focus on the field just along the X axis,
所以  如果你专注于沿 X 轴的电场
instead of decaying in proportion to 1 over R,
它就不再与距离成反比
this combined effect decays much more gently.
这种叠加效应的衰减  要缓慢得多
In the extreme,
在极端情形下
you can get something arbitrarily close to those
你还可以得到无限趋近于正弦波的曲线
pure sine wave propagations we were illustrating earlier
if at some distance away
做法是  在够远的地方
you have a large number of charges
让这样一整片电荷  同步摇摆
oscillating in sync with each other like this.
One thing that's worth emphasizing
有一点需要强调
when you see light illustrated with a sine wave like this
当你看见像这样画成正弦波的光
is that even that wave is being drawn in two or three dimensions,
即便画的是二维或者三维的图象
it's only describing the electric field along a one dimensional line,
它也只是在描述沿着一维直线的电场
namely the base of all those vectors.
即向量的箭尾所在的直线
It's just that to draw the vectors,
只是为了画出这些向量
you have to venture off of that line.
不可避免要脱离这条直线
Great, so one of the last important things to highlight
好  回到糖水实验之前  我们还要谈谈偏振
before we get back to the sugar water is polarization.
And everything I've been showing,
刚刚的演示里面
the driving charge is just oscillating along a single direction,
源电荷只是沿着一个方向振荡
like the Z axis,
比方说 Z 方向
and this causes linearly polarized light.
线偏振光就是这样产生的
But it doesn't have to happen like that.
但这并非铁律
For example, if I set the charge rotating in a little circle along the YZ plane,
比方说  让电荷在 YZ 平面的一个小圆上旋转
meaning its acceleration vector is also rotating in a little circle,
那么加速度向量也同样在圆上旋转
notice what the field looks like.
注意电场长什么样
This is known aptly enough as circularly polarized light.
这就叫做圆偏振光  名字很贴切
Honestly, it's easiest to think about for just one point of the electric field.
坦率地说  只考虑电场的一点会简单不少
What it means for light to be circularly polarized is that at that point,
在这一点上  圆偏振光
the electric field vector is just rotating in a circle.
对应的电场强度也在一个圆上旋转
People often find circular polarization a little confusing
经常有人觉得圆偏振光不好理解
and I suspect part of the reason for that is that
我觉得原因之一是它很难用静态图示呈现
it's hard to illustrate with static diagram,
but also it's a little confusing when you try to think about the full electric field.
但另一方面  要是考虑整个电场的分布  又容易眼晕
For example, here's what the field looks like on the XY plane
比方说  让电荷沿圆周旋转  XY 平面上电场长这样
when I set that little charge rotating in a circle.
It's certainly very beautiful, I could look at this all day
非常漂亮  我能盯着它看一天
but you can understand why it might feel a little confusing.
但你也会发现它确实有点令人迷惑
The very last thing I'll mention is that
最后要指出的是
while everything here is a classical description of light,
虽然这里全都是对光的经典描述
the important points still hold up in quantum mechanics.
但那些要点在量子力学中依然成立
You still have propagating waves,
波依然在传播
there's still polarization that can be either linear or circular.
也有线偏振或者圆偏振
The main difference with quantum mechanics is that
量子力学下的最大不同在于
the energy in this wave
波中的能量不是连续变化的  有些反常识
doesn't scale up and down continuously like you might expect,
it comes in discrete little steps.
而是离散地阶跃着变化的
I have another video goes into more detail
我还有另一个视频更清楚地展现这一点
but for our purposes, thinking about it classically is fine.
但是回答我们的问题  经典的图景就够用了
Part of the reason I wanted to go through that is because,
我想讲刚才的内容的一个原因在于
frankly it's just very fun to animate
坦白说  做这些动画很有意思
and I like an excuse for a fundamental lesson.
我也乐得有借口给观众补补课
But now let's turn back to our demo
但我们先回到开始的演示实验
and see how we can build up an intuition for some of our key questions,
看看要如何建立起直觉  来回答这些关键问题
starting from this very basic premise that
而切入点就是这个很基础的前提：
shaking a charge in one location
即在一点处晃动一个电荷
causes a shake to another charge a little bit later.
另一个电荷稍后也会随之晃动
And let's start by actually skipping ahead to question number three:
我们直接跳到问题 3 来开始吧
why do we see the diagonal stripes?
为什么会看到斜的条纹呢
To think about this,
要分析这个问题  首先设想管子侧面有一个观察者
you need to imagine an observer to the side of the tube
and then for a particular pure colour, say red,
然后选定一个纯色  例如红色
if the observer looks in the tube and sees that colour,
如果这个观察者看向管子  可以看到这个颜色的光
it's because light of that colour
这是因为这种颜色的光
has bounced off something at that point in the tube
在管子内的这一点上发生了散射
and then propagated towards the eye of the observer.
并最终传播到观察者眼中
Sometimes when people talk about light bouncing off of things,
有时  当人们提及光的散射
the implied mental image
他们脑海中的画面
is something like a projectile ricocheting off of some object
是一个子弹之类的物体  撞上某些东西
heading off in some random direction.
并向某个随机的方向反弹
But the better mental image to hold in your mind is that
但一种更好的想象方式是
when the propagating light waves caused by some wiggling charge
当电荷振荡产生的光波在传播中
reach some second charge causing it to wiggle,
碰到了另一个电荷  使其振荡时
that secondary wiggle results in its own propagation.
次生的振荡又产生了新的光波
And for the animation on screen,
屏幕上的动画演示了
that propagation goes back to the first charge
新的光波回到第一个电荷的地方
which itself causes a propagation towards the second
并引发了向第二个电荷的光波
and this is what it looks like in a very simplified situation
在这种高度简化的情形下  这看起来
for light to bounce back and forth between 2 charges.
像光在两个电荷之间往返
If you have some concentrated beam of polarized light
如果让一束集中的偏振光
interacting with some charge causing it to wiggle up and down,
与电荷相互作用  使之上下振荡
then these resulting second order propagations are most strong
那么引发出的光波最强的方向
in the directions perpendicular to the direction of polarization.
会与偏振方向垂直
In some sense, you could think of light as bouncing off of that charge
在某种意义上  你可以认为光在那个电荷上发生了反弹
but the important point is that it doesn't bounce in all directions equally.
但关键在于  它反弹的方向是不均匀的
It's strongest perpendicular to the wiggle direction
其在与振荡方向垂直的方向上最强
but gets weaker in all of the other directions.
在其它方向上都相对弱
So, think about our setup.
因此  联系到我们的问题
And for a particular frequency of light,
对于某个特定频率的光
how likely it is that an observer
看向管中某一个特定点的观察者  有多大概率能够看见光呢
looking at a particular point in the tube will see that light.
Again, the key phenomenon with sugar water, which we have yet to explain,
请回想  我们还没解释的关于糖水的那个关键现象：
is that the polarization direction
光波偏振的方向
is slowly getting twisted as it goes down the tube.
在沿管子传播的时候  是逐渐扭转的
So, suppose the observer was looking at a point like this one
因此  假定观察者正在看向某个点  比如这里
where the polarization direction happens to be straight up and down,
此时偏振方向刚好直上直下
then the second order propagations resulting from wiggling charges at that point
那个点处的电荷振荡  带来的二阶的光波
are most strong along the plane where the observer is.
刚好在观察者所在的平面处达到峰值
So the amount of red that they see at that point would look stronger.
因此在那个点  他们能看到最强的红光
By contrast,
但反言之
if they were looking at a different point in the tube like this one
如果他看向另一个点  例如这个点
where the wiggling direction is closer to being parallel to the line of sight,
振荡方向和视线几乎平行
then the direction where the scattering is strongest
那么光强最大的散射方向
is not at all aligned with the observer
与观察者根本没有对齐
and the amount of red they see is only going to be very weak.
他所见的红光将会非常微弱
And looking at our actual physical setup,
在实际实验中
if we first pass the light through a filter showing only the red,
如果我们先让光线通过红色的滤光片
we see exactly this effect in action.
就能清晰地看到这种现象
As you scan your eyes along the tube,
当视线沿着管子移动时
the intensity of red that you see
你会看到红色逐渐变弱  直至消失
goes from being high to being low where it's almost black,
back to being high again.
然后又重新亮起来
As an analogy,
打个比方
imagine there was a ribbon going down the tube
如果有一条丝带沿着管道延伸
always aligned with the polarization direction for this color,
始终与这一颜色的偏振方向平齐
then putting yourself in the shoes of the observer,
可以想象一下作为观测者
when you look at points where the ribbon appears very thin,
丝带看起来细的位置
you're going to see very little red light.
就是红光微弱的地方
Whereas if you scan your eyes over the points where the ribbon appears thicker,
而丝带看上去宽的位置
you're going to see more red light.
就是红光更亮的地方
One thing that's nice about this
有趣的是
is that if we try it for various different colors,
如果对不同颜色的光作以上的分析
you can actually see
可以发现
how the twisting rates are different for each one of the colors.
不同色光扭转率有所不同
Notice with red light,
对于红光来说
the distance between where it appears brightest
它看起来最亮和最暗的地方  间隔相对长
and where it appears darkest is relatively long.
Whereas if you look down the colours of the rainbow,
如果按照彩虹的顺序看下去
that distance between the brightest point and the darkest point
那么最亮和最暗处之间的距离会越来越短
gets lower and lower.
So, what you're seeing in effect is how red light twists slowly
这里看到的现象  反映了红光扭转得比较慢
whereas light waves with higher frequencies get twisted more aggressively.
而更高频的光扭转得更为明显
But still, you might wonder
但你可能还是想知道
why the boundaries between light and dark points appear diagonal.
为什么亮区和暗区之间的分界线看起来是斜的
Why is it that in addition to having variation
为什么不仅在视线左右移动时
as you scan your eyes from left to right,
看到的亮度会发生变化
there's also variation as you scan your eyes
在视线上下移动时  亮度也会有变化呢
from the top of the tube to the bottom.
This has less to do with what's going on in the tube
这就和管子里的事情关系不大了
and more to do with a matter of perspective.
这是视角的问题
Take a moment to think about
想象一下
many different parallel beams of light
许多束平行的光  从上到下布满整个管子
ranging from the top of the tube to the bottom.
At the beginning, all of these light waves are wiggling up and down
一开始  所有光线都在上下振荡
and as you pass through the tube
在光线穿过管道时
and the effects of the sugar water somehow twists these directions
糖水以某种方式将它们的振荡方向扭转
because they are all passing through the same amount of sugar,
因为它们通过的糖水的量相同
they are getting twisted by the same amounts.
所以扭转的幅度也相同
So, at all points, the polarization of these waves are parallel to each other.
于是  在每一点上  这些波的偏振方向相互平行
If you are the observer and you look at the top most point here,
如果你是观察者  当你看到最上面
its wiggling direction is essentially parallel to the line of sight.
这一点处光的振荡方向与视线平行
So the light scattering from that point
因此那一点散射出的光线
is basically not going to reach your eyes at all.
基本就不会到达你的眼中
It should appear black.
那么看起来就是黑的
But if you scan your eyes down the tube,
但当你逐渐向下看
the angle between the line of sight and the wiggling direction changes
视线和振荡方向的夹角发生改变
and so there will be at least some component of red light
至少有一部分红光能散射入你的眼睛
scattering towards the eye.
So, as you scan your eyes from top to bottom,
因此  当你从上往下扫视的时候
the amount of a particular color you see might vary,
你看到的颜色的光强也在变化
say from dark to light.
例如这样从暗到亮
The full demo that has white light
实验用白光进行展示
is basically a combination of all these pure colour patterns
也就是所有色光的混合
that go from light to dark to light
因此从亮到暗再到亮
with diagonal boundaries between the intense points and the weak points.
亮暗之间分界线是斜的
Hence why you see diagonal boundaries between the colours inside the tube.
所以你才会在不同颜色之间  看到斜的分界线
And now at last let's turn to the heart of the matter
最后我们回到核心问题
and try to explain why interactions with sugar
为什么偏振光遇上了糖  会发生这样的扭转
would make light twist like this in the first place.
It's related to the idea that
这与光在介质中传播时速度看似变慢有关
light seems to slow down as it passes through a given medium.
For example, if you look at the crests of a light wave as it goes into water,
如果你仔细观察光的波峰
the crests through the water are travelling about 1.33 times slower
波峰在水中传播时会比在真空中时慢大约1.33倍
than the crest of that wave would travel in a vacuum.
This number is what's called the "Index of Refraction" for water.
这个比例就是水的折射率
In a bit, what I'd like to show is how this index of refraction can be explained
以后我会介绍  解释折射率这一概念的一个方法是
by analyzing how the initial light wave shakes all the charges in the material
去分析入射光波对材料中电荷的振荡
and how the resulting second order propagations
以及由此产生的二阶的传播  是怎样与原始光波叠加的
super impose with that original light wave.
For right now I'll just say that the interactions with each layer of the material
但眼下我们只需要知道  与每层介质的作用
ends up having the effect of slightly shifting back the phase of the wave.
会使光的相位略微滞后
And on the whole, this gives the overall appearance
整体而言  看起来就像
that that wave moves slower as it passes through the material.
光波在材料中传播时变慢了
Skipping ahead to what's going on with sugar,
我们先去讲讲糖的事
the relevant property of sucrose here is that
蔗糖在这个过程中起作用的性质
it's what's called a chiral molecule.
是蔗糖分子的手性
Meaning it's fundamentally different from its mirror image.
手性指的是一个分子和它的镜像截然不同
You could never reorient it in space to become identical to its mirror image.
不管你再怎么进行平移与旋转  都不会相同
It's like a left hand or a right hand.
就像你的左手和右手
Or another much simpler example of a chiral shape is a spiral.
另一个更简单明了的例子是这个螺旋形状
If I take this right handed spiral,
这里有一个右手螺旋
then its mirror image is a left handed spiral
它的镜像  是左手螺旋
and no matter how you try to rotate and reorient that first one,
不论你怎样旋转和翻转第一个螺旋
it will never become identical to the second.
它都不可能变得和第二个一样
What's going on then is that the presence of a chiral molecule in the water like this
我们在水中加入蔗糖这种手性分子时
introduces an asymmetry when it comes to interactions with light,
就在与光的作用中引入了非对称性
specifically circularly polarized light.
特别是对圆偏振光而言
It turns out that the amount this chiral molecule slows down,
这种手性分子会让圆偏振光变慢
say left handed circularly polarized light,
但左旋圆偏振光变慢的程度
is different from the amount that it slows down right handed circularly polarized light.
和右旋圆偏振光变慢的程度是不同的
Effectively, there is not one index of refraction but two.
可以说  折射率不只有一个  而是有两个
Now, you might say that seems irrelevant to our setup.
你可能会觉得  这与我们的实验不相关啊
Since we are very deliberately shining in linearly polarized light,
因为我们照明时有意使用了线偏振光
there is no circularly polarized light
而不是圆偏振光
but actually there is a sense in which linearly polarized light
但其实  在某种意义下  线偏振光就是
is equal parts left handed and right handed circularly polarized light.
由等量的左旋和右旋的圆偏振光组成的
Here, focus your attention on
注意观察在波中直上直下的这一个向量
just one vector in this wave wiggling straight up and down,
which is to say polarized in the Z direction.
它在沿Z方向偏振
Notice how it's possible to express this vector as a sum of two rotating vectors.
这个向量可以表示为两个正在旋转的向量之和
One of them rotating at a constant rate counterclockwise
它们以固定的速率  一个顺时针转
and the other one rotating clockwise.
一个逆时针转
Adding them together, tip to tail,
首尾相接向量相加
results in a vector oscillating on a line.
得到的就是沿一条线振荡的向量
In this case, it's a vertical line
这里我们展示了垂直方向的线
but that direction can change
但振荡方向可以根据两个旋转向量的相位而变化
based on the phase of the two vectors we're adding together.
Here, let me throw up a couple labels
现在我们来记录一下  两个向量分别转了多少
to keep track of how much each one of those two vectors has rotated in total
and then every now and then, I'm going to slow down that first vector a little bit
并且时不时  我会把第一个向量的转速调慢一点
and I want you to notice what happens to their sum.
来看看它们的和会怎样变化
Well, every time I slow it down,
每次减慢向量的转速
effectively knocking back its phase a little bit,
也等效于滞后其相位
it causes the linearly wiggling sum to wiggle in a slightly different direction.
都会让这个线性振荡的和向量  方向稍微改变
So, if the circularly polarized light wave represented by that left vector
所以当一种圆偏振光  也就是画在左侧的向量
gets slowed down a little bit every time it runs across a sugar molecule
被每个它经过的糖分子减速后
or at least slow down more than its oppositely rotating counterpart would,
或者说  相对于反向旋转的偏振光  减速更多时
the effect on the sum is to slowly rotate the direction of linear polarization.
两种圆偏振光之和形成的线偏振光  就会跟着缓慢旋转
And hence, as you look at slices further and further down the tube,
因此  我们在更靠后的截面上观察这束光时
the polarization direction does indeed get twisted
就发现偏振方向果然以我们所描述的方式  发生了偏转
the way we were describing earlier
representing how the composite effects with
这说明许许多多糖分子的叠加效应
many many many different sugar molecules
are slightly different for left handed light than they are for right handed light.
对左旋和右旋的圆偏振光  确实略有区别
As a nice way to test whether you understood everything up to this point,
作为一个测试你理解程度的小例子
see if just by looking at the direction of the diagonal slices on our tube,
你能通过观察我们管子的斜面
you can deduce which kind of light the sugar is slowing down more.
来判断对糖水而言  哪种光更慢吗
Left handed light or right handed light.
是左旋  还是右旋  的圆偏振光呢
I'll call this a partial answer to our question number one
我想这算是对问题 1 的部分解答
because it still leaves us wondering
毕竟我们还没有说清楚
why there is an index of refraction in the first place
首先为什么会有折射率这回事
and how exactly it might depend on the polarization of the light
也没有解释  为什么折射率与偏振有关
not just the material it's passing through.
而不只是跟介质的材料有关
Also, like I said at the start,
以及我开头时也说过
a robust enough intuition here should also answer for us
一个足够好的直觉猜测  应当包含
why the strength of this effect would depend on the frequency of the light.
为什么这种效应  还和光的频率有关
At this point, I think we've covered quite enough for one video,
但就一期视频而言  我们已经讲得足够多了
so I'll pull out a discussion covering the origins of the index of refraction
所以我们将在另一期视频中  讨论折射率的来源
to a separate video.